hello and welcome
everyone it's July 22nd 2024 this is
active inference guest stream
82.3 the projective wave theory of
Consciousness Robert Warden will give a
presentation and we have several others
to join and comment and give their
insights so thank you everyone for
joining and Robert please begin the
presentation and also Robert close the
YouTube on your side all
good sorry
I've it's coming through on my loud
speaker which is a problem yeah it's all
good like
ready okay so this is a a talk about the
projective wave theory of Consciousness
and there's already a paper about it on
archive this month so you can look at
the paper if you like but let me start
by describing roughly the road mapap for
the talk um the projective wave theory
is very closely related to the
projective conscious model PCM and we're
fortunate to have three of the authors
of that model on the call today but I'm
going to give this talk in four
different parts um the first part is
talking about data and the idea is that
any Theory of Consciousness has to fit
the data has to fit some data in order
for us to believe it and so the question
is what kinds of data is there about
Consciousness that the theory has to fit
and I shall be arguing there the main
kind of data we have is spatial
Consciousness so that's part one of the
Talk part two I shall talk about the
projective Consciousness model PCM and
to my mind the big virtue of the PCM is
that it does predict account for just
that the spatial nature of cons ious and
in that it's a great deal it does a
great deal better than many neural
theories of
Consciousness and I shall probably pause
at that point after Parts one and two
and and have discussion about the the
first two points there but before that I
think the PCM has great strengths but I
think in common with all neural theories
of Consciousness it has three problems
and I shall talk about what those
problems are but I shall emphasize that
those problems are not specific to the
PCM if you buy into the classical neurom
model of the brain that neurons do
everything then whatever your theory of
Consciousness I think you're going to
have these problems and so in order to
get out of those problems we have to do
something that's not in the classical
neural model that assumes that neurons
in the brain do everything so we have to
add something to the PCM and the
something we have to add is there in
three the assumption we're going to add
to it is quite a big one it's an
assumption that there is a wave in the
brain which stores 3D spatial
information in other words neurons don't
do
everything and then part four of the
talk I shall bring those two and three
together to a projective wave theory of
Consciousness and talk a little about
firstly how that solves the neural
problems but secondly how it fits the
data and some more General
considerations about it so that is the
root map for the talk
so um we start off with what are the
reasons to believe some Theory whether a
theory of Consciousness or anything else
why do we believe it basically we
believe a theory because it fits data
and it there's a complexity measure here
that needs to fit more data which you
can measure in bits if you like than the
complexity of the assumptions you put
into it if you just put in a huge number
of assumptions and fit a small amount of
data that's no use so there's a kind of
basian balance between the assumptions
you put into a theory and the data it
fits and I've Illustrated the basian
balance a pair of scales here and I've
uh measured the the complexity of the
theory and the amount of data it tests
by a so-called zip test which simply
says you describe these things in text
files you zip them up and you see how
big they are so established theories in
science like the theories of physics or
chemistry have a hugely positive base
inbalance they have quite few
assumptions and they account for huge
amounts of data so how can we get to
that point with the theory of
Consciousness how can a theory of
Consciousness produce a positive Bas
imbalance between its assumptions and
the data it accounts for so the question
arises what is the data we have to test
theories of Consciousness and there's a
big problem which is well known that
Consciousness is a private experience so
there's not much public data about it
but there are several kinds of data we
can use such as data about levels of
consciousness alertness and and being
asleep and so on uh data about qual and
now they are problematic because they're
private phenomena but nevertheless you
can two people can agree something about
similarity scales of their
qualia like different colors being
similar or different and the form C is
the shapes of things in spatial cons
Consciousness and I shall argue that the
main manifestation of Consciousness
which we have what we're experiencing
right now is a 3D spatial model of the
world around us and that 3D model is
very detailed and quite faithful to the
real world around us and so that has a
large information
content um going down the list there's
conscious imagination there is conscious
of the self there are anomalies and
illusions of Consciousness and there is
the hard problem if you like the
existence of Consciousness itself now I
shall argue that point C the shape of
spatial Consciousness gives us much more
data to test any Theory than any other
type of
data so what's the testable data in
spatial
Consciousness spatial Consciousness is
like a 3D model of the real world around
you that's what you're experiencing
right now and it has a lot of the
geometry of the real world and and
particularly straight lines in
Consciousness correspond to straight
lines in the real world and you can test
this I won't go into the details of how
so this agreement between our conscious
experience which is quite information
rich and the real world around us which
is obviously information risk gives a
lot of data to test any Theory Of
Consciousness and I suggest roughly
gives a thousands of bits even in a few
seconds and I shall suggest that no
other form of data about Consciousness
comes anywhere close to this in terms of
testable information content so if you
really want to prove your theories right
then it's got to account for the spatial
form of Consciousness if you're going to
believe it and down at the right here I
put my contention that spatial
Consciousness is if you like the element
in the room Consciousness
Theory so we have to consider how the
brain does spal
cognition and all anal brains pretty
much do that they have to understand 3D
local space for a very fundamental
reason as to control their every
movement to move every movement of their
limbs they have to understand 3D space
around them and there's been huge
selection pressure to do this well and
we believe that animals do it very well
even insects do it quite
well and also it appears that most of
the animal brain is devoted to that now
if we assume a basian hypothesis about
cognition then the way animals do that
is to build a maximum likelihood 3D
model of local space in their brains
from their sense sense
data so it becomes fairly natural to
expect that spatial Consciousness is
going to be linked to this spatial model
the question is is it a purely neural
model as in classical neural models of
the brain and if it is how does neuron
firing represent 3D space and this is
quite a difficult problem and really
there are very few
uh viable solutions to it but I shall
switch now I shall put that problem on
one side and switch to the projective
Consciousness model PCM which has been
developed by David and his collaborator
since about
2017 and it's built on the free energy
principle so it's based on a basian
model of local space in the
brain and for neural for its neural
process model it assumes the process
model of the free energy principle and
so the PCM assumes that the brain holds
a 3D projective transform model of local
ukian space and the key thing is that
PCM then predicts that spatial conscious
Consciousness is like that model and
this is a a very good prediction it
agrees very well the data for instance
the trivial fact that straight lines in
your Consciousness are straight lines in
the real
world so the PCM has a good Bas in
Balance I should say this is very
distinctive amongst many the of
Consciousness they very few of them talk
about the spatial nature of
Consciousness and if they do they
probably treat it a bit of an
afterthought but the PCM puts it uh out
in the front and I think that's a very
positive feature of it and it has a good
Basi in balance and it does make various
other predictions which people have
talked about in the papers makes
predictions about illusions of
Consciousness and makes predictions
about predective imagination and
planning
actions now I don't think those are
quite as significant in the Bas in
balance in the agreement with the data
as the basic agreement with the form of
Consciousness right now uh Consciousness
from sense data but I shall say the PCM
has three difficulties I shall emphasize
they're not difficulties of the PCM
alone I believe they are difficulties of
any neural theory of of Consciousness
and and I'll just list them briefly here
because there going to be a slide
describing them the first difficulty is
neural selection how do we pick out just
those neurons which cause
Consciousness from all the others that
don't and the second one is neural
precision and speed we know that our
conscious model of space is a very
detailed and precise one can you do that
with neuron firing I would suggest you
can't and the third one is a complex
decoding problem that uh anyway I'll
come on to that so I'll describe these
three in a minute but the emphasis is
that they are not just problems of the
PCM they are difficulties for any neural
Theory Of Consciousness for instance IIT
or Global neural neural workspace Theory
and so on so what are the three
difficulties the neural selection
problem most neurons in the brain are
not linked to Consciousness we know that
from cortical lesions which don't
interrupt Consciousness or the
cerebellum or Beyond Mera is written
quite extensivity about this but neuron
theories of Consciousness say that the
activity of some neurons causes
conscious ious and not others so the
question is how are those special
neurons selected and as far as I know
there's no sound physical basis to pick
out some neurons from all the others so
you build in some selection assumptions
into your hypothesis but those form a
deit in your basian balance so they're a
debit for any neural Theory Of
Consciousness the second difficulty
whoops uh all
right second difficulty is how do
neurons represent space now there are
several possible ways of having neurons
representing 3D space you can represent
2D space all right in neur can you
return to sharing the the screen oh
sorry I've lost sharing have I all good
so um how do neurons represent 3D
space there are several ways they might
do it but they all have problems of
precision and
speed for instance there is a basin
computational model of how animals build
3D internal model of space from their
sense data and this is already on one of
live the aii live streams at this
YouTube address but that model shows
that in order to build a 3D model of
space even even for a small animal like
a bee you need memory storage errors to
be roughly the order 1% as small as that
whereas if you model neurons accurately
properly they don't give you this
Precision because in a
neuron most theoretical models of
neurons are ideal abstract neurons who
out whose outputs are real variables of
high precision and that's shown in the
top of this picture here whereas
actually neurons outputs are Spike
trains which in the short time scale
gives very limited Precision for
instance in a fifth of the second
possible time scale for
Consciousness you may get about 10
pulses and that gives you a Precision of
only
30% in that time scale so the Precision
you get from neuro
representations is very different from
what you need to build a decent 3D model
or what we experience in
Consciousness and this I think hasn't
been really spotted very much because
most of the neural models that you see
in the literature they don't model Spike
trains it's enough to model networks of
neurons and so they use abstract precise
neurons so that's the second difficulty
how can neurons store a precise and
responsive fast model of 3D space like
the one we
experience finally uh what's happened
here can you see that change third
difficulty the third difficulty is what
I call the hard triangle because
conscious experience which you see in
this picture here is a faithful hardly
distorted model of the real world
there's the real world a and there's
Consciousness awareness C but what the
models we have found in the brain are
two-dimensional models and very
distorted models and so they're many
different models and they're highly
complex encodings to get from A to
B so if you want to get back from B to C
you have to do very complex decoding to
undo all the complex coding that most
species brains do and so ABC is a hard
triangle you have to have complex
decoding assumptions in any neural
Theory Of Consciousness and the worst
thing of that maybe is that the decoding
has to be species specific it can't be
Universal
decoding so those are the three
difficulties for any neural Theory Of
Consciousness including the PCM I
believe so that's where we've got to
I've covered topics one and two of this
talk and now I think we'll break for any
discussion or
contributions thank you very much Robert
for your presentation um up to now I can
follow it very well I think it's uh you
point out very important uh
issues uh I should say and perhaps you
know with scan that from the standpoint
of the PCM even though indeed uh we have
framed it in the context of active
influence and more specifically the free
energy
principle um we do not necessarily uh
um
um unil it does not necessarily unil
that we buy or we endorse or we believe
in uh the current neural network models
that are used in this context personally
I've been a neuroscientist for many
years done a lot of electrophysiology
Legion work with human patient also I
worked with rodent I've done a lot of
functional Imaging and modeling and at
some point in my career I thought that I
did not understand the brain well enough
and I stopped uh doing Neuroscience I
stopped carrying quote unquote about the
brain and uh for us what is the most
important in the PCM at this point is
all you said is that we can capture some
aspect of the phenomenology that seem
essential etc etc so personally I have
given up at this point uh trying to
um devise or figure out a any you know
realistic uh neural network models and
when you take just one neuron as you
said uh Robert it's a universe you just
think about
how receptors are up or down regulated
through fast gene expression or dritic
trees and their complexities and their
geometry plays a role in computation I
don't believe that the uh spiking uh of
the of the neurons which we often call
the output of the neuron are necessarily
where we should be looking at uh and I
don't know where we should be looking at
I I committed a a a an odd papers a long
time ago in
2015 uh in which I kind of said well I
explain why I had given up hope at this
point uh about brain science to account
for that because I think we don't
understand the brain I think there are
principle we haven't figure out figured
out yet by far and my um guess was that
a bit like by analogy with computer
science there are layers of abstraction
mechanism of virtualization that hide
the detail of the hardware uh which we
don't understand at all uh and so so far
it's a very open-ended thing so to me
what matters the most about the PCM at
this point is uh with respect to the
brain it is neutral we don't know at
this point I have absolutely no
hypothesis except very gross anatomy
hypothesis but or some you know possible
details about you know but you write
uh that's the hard problem and
personally I have given up on trying to
account for
it thanks I found so much to agree with
there and so yeah we we don't understand
what's going on in the brain maybe
neurons are doing something much more
complicated than simple Spike trains but
uh maybe there's also this wave any
we'll talk about that Carl Ken do you
have any comments at this stage
uh Carl you want to go or I can if you
don't mind I'll just follow up with I
completely agree with what um deavid
said um and I I will say my own sort of
approach to the problem has always been
sort of agnostic about the underlying
realization so I've kind of started
from all you know in my own thinking
anyway always from the point of view of
phenomenology with some kind of um
you might say
General acceptance of some sort of
physicalism but agnostic about the
details of that physicalism so agnos
about whether it's um exactly what goes
on in the brain or what level and so on
um I I guess I've tended
to even though I I agree you can't
exclude it AR priori I've tended to kind
of think well quantum mechanical
theories are probably barking up the
wrong tree but but that's just like my
gut on that um and then personally sorry
personally Ken at this point I'm so
confused about the brain and about the
physical nature of the universe that I'm
even totally open that the whole thing
is quantum I have no idea okay yeah as I
said it's just sort of like my gut on
that but not I can't really defend
it in detail for a number of reasons um
owing to my own ignorance um but and I
just add that uh and I I agree I think
the way you presented the PCM generally
was exactly right um you did mention
that we do have something to say about
imagination like action planning and
about um anomalies and Illusions and and
we you know we agree with you I think
that the main set of data we aim to
capture or the the spatial the spatial
component of Consciousness then
perspectival spatial component like you
know the project what we use projective
geometry to capture but then we do try
to as you know try to derive certain
other bits of parts of the relevant data
from that basis so accounting for
illusions um like the Moon Illusion and
the ases room illusion um and accounting
for um imaginative action planning and
also I should add some data about
self-awareness so we have a paper on um
self-awareness in this context as well
um so yeah I think that's all I got so
far but this is this has been very
interesting so far right thanks
again Carl
on Carl gonna make any comments um no
I'm just enjoying this as a spectator uh
batting for both sides uh
uh one comment it seems to me that we're
focusing on the distinction between
principles um about how the brain makes
sense of its world and the process
theories that attend those principles in
terms of instantiation and there's a um
an agnostic approach I think you can
take in relation to process theories uh
so I'm interested to see how much um
Robert's Focus will be on the process
Theory and the actual substrates which
um
um you know I think is um interesting
from the point of view of um actually
simulating this kind of um
inference um and also uh being able to
reproduce it in silico in terms of you
know create creating a a kind of
artificial intelligence that has this
this kind of competence and so uh there
may be a more pragmatic Focus um I was
intrigued by the previous slide um this
this hard triangle
um where you
yeah just go to it there yeah uh this
yeah it I I I didn't quite um resonate
with this uh I think for a start the
Notions of encoding and decoding for
people like me would should be usefully
unpacked um so everything in terms of
belief updating is some kind of mapping
or morphism or
relationship
um so I'm assuming mapping is is a good
word for it yeah okay so the world
generates sensory inputs um and then the
brain um represents those inputs I mean
for B you just imagine you know the
visual cortex with a highly distorted
version of space in it all around the
fvia and so on and all the other
cortical maps are highly distorted
representation of space and somehow you
have to tramel those back into an
undistorted representation so you've got
to decode the encoding that's gone
on I see
so right so the conscious awareness is
still part of the brain somewhere
it must come from the brain somehow I
think yes that we
all I see so you're using encoding and
decoding and a sort of
um
uh distorting
undistorting it's like a distorting
mirror you got undistorted but I guess
it relates to car distinction between
neural neural substrate and process
Theory because indeed if you look at the
classical sort of quote unquote 2D maps
in the cerebral
cortex Vis cortex with your retinotopy
where you see a lot of deformation but
also somato sensory ctis you think about
the classical you know map of the body
uh uh and you are ask saying well if
that's the way it is kind of represented
quote unquote at the level of that
substrate then since it is deform and we
don't experience it that way we should
somehow have a process on top of that
that use some morphism to transform this
deformation I'm saying our Theory Of
Consciousness has to tell us how that
how that unscrambling Distortion
happens yeah but I believe that the
level of observation that we are
considering here for instance those 2D
quote unquote 2D because they are not
really 2D but uh cortical Maps uh
retinotopic or somatotopic or you know
topic maps are a very quote unquote low
level of processing
uh which might be very far away from
yeah what is going there might be some
other super representation somewhere but
we not found it yet yeah and it might
not be visible at the level of the
anatomy well yeah those are alternatives
I agree okay so sorry Carl I interrupted
but I wanted to make this precision too
yeah
no that clarifies it thank
you but Carl I mean I think we can all
be agnostic about certain things in the
process model I think you and I at least
are not agnostic about
basm yeah I I would put sort of you know
the notion of
um sentience of the kind we're talking
about as a process of basing belief
updating I I put that at the sort of
principle level sort of at the mechanics
that that that doesn't commit to uh
an infrastructure or a realization or a
process that that
realizes that uh um you know that kind
of principle or that kind of uh
mechanics um so I think the spatial wave
theory is really a commitment to a
process Theory um that could you know
happily accommodate Basin belief
updating and its particular application
in the context of spatial perception and
projective you know the projective
Consciousness
model you're
muted um oh yes
hear
me good yes okay so moving on
um so we've done one and two and what
we're going to do in three is add
something to the PCM and the thing going
to add is not a little thing it's the
Assumption the hypothesis that neurons
don't do everything but there is a wave
in the brain which stores 3D spatial
information so that's what I'm going to
talk about
next so here's the hypothesis there is a
wave in the brain that represents 3D
space so it assumes there's some nearly
spherical region of the brain with a
diameter D and it holds waves which
couples to neurons and and there are the
sphere is Illustrated and a couple of
waves wavelength Lambda 2 that Green
Wave and wavelength Lambda one a shorter
wavelength that red wave and those waves
represent things in space and they
represent the red thing R1 and the green
thing R2 so there's a kind inverse
relationship there the shorter the
wavelength the longer the distance to
the thing that's being represented but
obviously if it's a if it's a spherical
region you can have waves in any
direction so you can represent any
direction and any distance up to a
maximum which is defined by the minimum
wavelength so that wave can represent
lots of different things and the
hypothesis is that that wave acts as a
working memory for space it's really
like a a hologram now one issue with
that is that if you want to represent
objects at very large distances away
then you get into wavelengths that's too
short so that's why you may need a
projective transform of space to pull in
those long distances to be able to
represent them on the brain on the wave
by the way the evidence for this wave is
going to be described in another uh
YouTube live stream which we're making
next week is going to be at that
address
so how well does a wave based spal
memory
form it can represent approximately D of
a Lambda cubed independent positions
which is quite a lot and it can give you
spatial Precision the order of Lambda
over D and the point is that this can
easily be 1% or better which is the
Precision you need so there are
significant benefits to wave storage it
has high capacity you can put many
objects in it it has high Precision it
can be fast and it has low spatial
Distortion it is just like a
hologram and it's a very simple direct
representation of space so a spoiler
looking ahead to part four of the talk
is that this is very much like spatial
Consciousness question is there any
evidence for such a wave I think there
is evidence and there's three kinds of
evidence first two comes from brain
anatomy because there are spherical
regions in the brain which are very well
suited to hold this W in the mamals
there is the thalamus and that's shown
in green on the left of the picture and
you can see it's approximately spheric
and that is very suitably connected for
holding spatial information it's
connected to all the sense data and it's
connected to all the bits of Cortex that
work out what to do with the sense data
and similarly in the insect brain there
is a a central body in the very center
of it that is approximately spherical
and it's very well preserved shape in
all insect species so those are both
pieces of evidence for a wave in the
brain there is a the place for
it uh so I believe there are three lines
of evidence for a wave one is the
computational Neuroscience which I've
mentioned before that spatial cognition
is a very important thing but neural
memory for it is too imprecise and too
slow whereas a wave storage model can
possibly overcome these problems so
that's the yellow evidence there
evidence from the insect central body
that is nearly round very Central very
well connected
and there's evidence from the M mum
Thalamus it's also round and well
connected but there's also what I call a
Smoking Gun for a wave in the thalamus
that if you don't assume a wave the
anatomy of the thalamus doesn't make
sense but I won't go into that in this
talk so together I believe these give
quite strong support for the wave
hypothesis in fact they give it a
probability of 0.5 approximately even if
you try and wait the odds against it as
I say you can see the discussion of this
in another YouTube live stream we're
about to make
so then that's on from part three to
part four of
talk assume there is a wave in the brain
which holds the near projective
transform of 3D space and this wave is
serving a very essential role to
understand space to control all
movements for any animal and the
hypothesis simply is the wave is the
origin of
Consciousness that neurons have nothing
to do with Consciousness at all it comes
entirely from the wave this solves three
problems the three problems that I
outlined before firstly the neural
selection problem youve no selection
problem because neurons have do with
Consciousness the Precision and speed
problem the wave has sufficient
precision and speed to do it and the
decoding problem the coding in the wave
is just a for your transform so it's a
very simple coding
encoding and it's very simple decoding
to give you back conscious experience so
it has solved those three problems of
neural
theories but the main thing is that spal
for like the PCM preserving the Merit of
the PCM the spatial form of
Consciousness agrees very well with our
conscious
experience it has to have has to be
projected because we need the project
transform to pull in objects from very
large distances to represent them by a
minimum wave length so in summary uh the
projective wave theory has a positive
Bas imbalance doesn't have any Nares
about it and it agrees very well with
the main source of data about
Consciousness so just some aspects of
this Theory what is the physical nature
of the wave a big objection might be
we've never seen in wave because I
believe uh it's probably not an
electromagnetic wave or electromagnetic
field and the main reason I believe that
is that electromagnetic fields on their
own don't store information for the time
periods we need to store information and
now electromagnetic fields might be part
of the answer but I think they're not
the whole
answer and the big question then is why
have we not detected this wave in brain
if it's been there all these years uh I
think the reason for that is we expect
if there is a wave representing space we
would expect it to evolve to have very
low intensity so its energy assumption
is very small and having that low
intensity we simply haven't known how to
look for
it now coming to Quantum possibilities
the wave might be a coherent Quantum
excitation and there's increasing
evidence that Quantum effects do have
play a role in biology and it might even
be a banan condensate a BC now those
examples of those are superconductors
and super fluids they're very rare state
in nature but the key thing about a BC
is a superconductor can hold information
for unlimited time so it would be good
for memory and they're a very rare and
distinctive state of matter and so if
you assume that Consciousness comes from
them you don't get to a trap of pan
psychism or it might not be a Quantum
effect because I think that this
question is entirely so we'll set that
on one side and that's future
exploration
there's an issue about the evolution of
Consciousness uh we know that
Consciousness is our Consciousness is
like the real world it's very like the
real world and the question is why is
this and you think well it must have
evolved that way because there some need
for it to be like the real real world
but in neural theories there's a problem
because neural computation in the brain
the classical neural model is classical
Dynamics not quantum physics and it's
local and so concept is a non-physical
non-local effect and they don't have any
effect on neurons firing so the result
is that Consciousness in a neural theory
has no causal effect on Fitness that
means there's no selection pressure on
it to make it the way it is so in a
neural Theory Of Consciousness we're
driven to this slightly awkward
conclusion that the special form of
Consciousness that we have is just a bit
of an accident that seems very
unlikely whereas in the objective wave
theory there is a good evolutionary
reason Consciousness being like it is
that is that 3D spatial cognition is
very
important wave is an essential part of
it so the wave has been shaped by
Evolution and it's been shaped to be
just like the real world because that's
the best way of controlling mve so
Consciousness then is determined by the
wave and that means Consciousness has
evolved to be like so the wave theory
solves another problem there
finally the unity of Consciousness uh
you may ask this question occasionally
why do I only have one Consciousness and
not several parallel
consciousnesses and this also is
something of a difficulty of neural
theories because we have plenty of
neurons in the brains have many parallel
consciousnesses and brains can do some
things in massive parallelism and if we
had multiple parallel Consciousness it
might be useful for instance of parallel
planning of actions to see which one
worked
that's a difficulty for neural theories
the wave theory doesn't have this
difficulty because it accounts for the
unity of Consciousness there's only one
wave in the brain that is the source of
Consciousness so there can only be one
Consciousness I think I'm on to the last
slide now pretty much the last slide if
this theory is taken serious it makes
Consciousness into a scientific problem
rather than a philosophical problem
because wave in the brain If a wave in
the brain is the key to understanding
Consciousness well if there's no wave
then this theory is wrong get about it
but there is a wave I think there are
very strong reasons to link it to
Consciousness because it has such a good
fit to
Consciousness so the exist whether or
not the wave exists that's a scientific
question it's not a question for
philosophy and I think there's a good
Prospect of answering it in the next 10
years so in 10 years time either this
Theory will be the only theory of
ousness or it'll be wrong and forgotten
I think that's a virtue in a
theory so um finally last slide on the
hard problem David charma's hard problem
the projected wave theory doesn't solve
that
problem what I would say about that is
all science has hard problems there is
the hard problem of Consciousness why is
conscious un link to matter there are
hard problems in physics like what is
space time or what is the most
fundamental particle or the hard problem
of cosmology why is there a universe so
hard problems just don't have an
answer scientists were like children
keeping asking why say why this why that
and we can go on asking why for as long
as we like so for instance for
fundamental particles we thought there
was matter we thought there were atoms
we got to protons we got to quarks and
we keep going on and we'll never get the
final answer but we still do science so
I'm not too worried about the hard
problem
Consciousness uh so that is all and uh
I've just laid out a few questions one
might want to discuss in the remaining
time maybe you could share your slide
again so we can see the question if you
have them on the
slide uh sorry is it not sharing now I
see the slide still um yeah so you can
leave it maybe check your view David and
then you can leave that up and we can
have a panel
discussion
okay well thanks a lot um those who are
here Ken and Carl and deid please feel
free to uh
comment and also people will write some
questions in the chat and and I'll read
one in if if you pause but anyone here
who'd like to give a reflection or or
any comments that would be
awesome could I go ahead
can you hear me yeah so uh if if I may I
I I basically agree with what you say
about the hard Pro just to take the very
last thing that you mentioned about the
hard problem and this is why earlier on
when you said that um you had kind of a
list of sort of um you know in your the
idea of the basian balance for theories
of Consciousness and you mentioned the
existence of Consciousness as itself
something that might be a problem for
all
neuronal theories of Consciousness I
think you did that in on a slide two any
Theory yeah yeah so I I agree I think
it's a problem for any Theory Of
Consciousness even the kind of um more
metaphysical theories that people who
reflect like Chalmers and others pansus
who reflect on the hard problem a
certain way end up with you can actually
raise the same set of questions for them
so there's really no progress there in
my opinion so in other words if if you
take the hard problem as a kind of
indication that um well Consciousness
couldn't be physical or or either that
or the physical world itself must just
be Consciousness which is kind of the
two directions they they go there I
think that's kind of misguided I mean we
we have to sort of um accept that our
ability to penetrate you know
cognitively AR priori into
nature of the cosmos is is limited so
our the best we can do is make models
and you know based on the phenomenology
and try to arrive at a model that would
give us some kind of neural uh or
physical to speak more broadly uh
physical um testable you know hypoth
hypotheses we can test about the
physical world what we think realizes
Consciousness and it seems to me like
that's exactly what you're doing and
that's what I would think is is right
too but I I did want to ask you um when
you say that um no neurons are linked to
Consciousness in your own model um do
you mean maybe I just don't understand
exactly but then they're not linked
directly to the Consciousness
NE but they're involved in the
realization of of the wave is that oh
they are abely abely they're controlling
the wave they're setting up the wave
they're all around the cortex they're
using sense data to to fix the wave and
it's the wave that makes
Consciousness okay and on the issue of
unity well so suppose we identify this
type of wave um I mean it's at least you
know conceivable that we would find
multiple such waves would you concl
conceivable I think the evidence in the
thalamus and the central body is one
wave okay and I think one wave is what
you need to understand one space around
you okay so but if you found multiple
such waves yeah absolutely that would be
an issue yeah okay I mean would you
conclude that there must be multiple
consciousnesses then in a single brain
or would you would you think that the
theory is wrong no I would have a
selection problem just like neuron
theories a selection problem selecting
neurons I'd have a problem selecting
which wave was
conscious I see H rather than conclude
that there are
multiple you want to avoid that and my
experience is I don't have multiple
conscience yes my right but that might
just be because only one of them gets to
report yeah absolutely you know like
like the way they you know I know it's
debatable but the way they um
you know often interpreted the the split
brain uh cases coming out of yeah good
question good question I mean I say one
wave but we have two thalami so the
Assumption there is that those waves are
linked and perhaps in split brain they
don't get
linked H okay I think two thalami have
one wave in them but that's a
deto I see and then when it comes to the
kind of wave
like so you you don't think it's an
electromagnetic wave uh you you you
think it might be a Bose Einstein
condens it that's that's the hypothesis
I think that Karen Smith once uh Flo
it's been around for some years yeah
Alexander Karen Smith in a and the book
uh that's the yeah not not the book on
the origin the famous book on the origin
of life but he wrote a book on
Consciousness back in the 9s I think um
yeah there was Michael Lockwood as well
in the 80s I think it's a long history
okay so H how um when you say that you
think we will'll be able to probe this
within the next 10 years I mean could
you sort of sketch how that might go how
we might be able yeah I mean just this
is not this is probing the idea of the
wave right as I say I think there are
those three pieces evidence there's
neural models that you can't build
decent neural models there is the
thalamus and there is the insect central
body I think we can go further on each
one of those we can test them we can
test the thalamus ideas much better
using connectome data we can test the
central body using connectome data and
we can test the computational models by
just trying to build them and see if we
get in so there is science to be done to
falsify this hypothesis and it may
succeed in falsifying
it okay um but how would you measure uh
such condensate I mean if you want to be
able to demonstrate the existence prop
ideally you'd like to actually directly
detect it I I think it's a bit like when
poy in the 1930s predicted the neutrino
he thought it absolutely impossible to
detect neutrinos and it took 25 years to
find it and I think it'll take a long
time to really find this wave in the
brain because it's very low intensity
probably and because we just don't know
how to look for it and I think we have
to do the biophysics until we had a
convincing case for I this kind of wave
then we can build a detector but until
then I think we won't detect it like
neutrino or like dark matter similar
thing predicted theoretically years ago
but still not
detected I'll read a question from the
live
chat
okay Andrea Val wrote thanks for sharing
ing such interesting ideas I wonder how
the PCM or 3D model can explain or deal
with the un/ consciousness of
emotions so where is affect and such in
this kind of spatialized model yeah so
you want to do in the PM first
David uh if it's okay Robert maybe you
have read some of recent work on that
but we we we we I have a specific
answer to that question if you yeah you
go first yeah sorry about that uh well
one things that uh we realized working
with that particular geometry is it
transform information in the sense of
information in space you can think about
distribution in space for instance that
are going to be changed by projective
transformation uh in a manner that
affect directly entropy so if something
is very far you know in you have some
uncertainty about the localization of
these things so there is a probability
function that represent that uncertainty
about localization of that thing uh uh
and there is only one thing in your
field of Consciousness to simplify the
problem uh then the entropy of the whole
Space if you if you consider the whole
3D space uh and some scalar on it that
would represent probabilities uh is uh
uh um is very small whereas uh when you
get closer for instance by imagination
through projective transformation that
anticipate action you get the object
closer and you transform also the
information the the variance if you wish
of your distribution so it become
broader so the entropy increase actually
as an effect of projective
transformation of the on the
distribution of information so how does
that relate to emotion what we uh
realized is that uh um it's can account
for some drives that are related to
exploration or exploratory Behavior or
search Behavior to reduce reduce
uncertainty or maximize
information uh and that just does that
so basically the projective
transformation uh uh by in virtue of
making probabilities function in space
uh change their shape as a function of
perspective taking if you wish until or
induce a drive to approach or avoid
things or in in in this context to
approach uh to have be approach Behavior
either through imagination or through
actual Behavior because that will
maximize information by increasing
entropy of the object and you have more
details so that's something that we
wrote a paper that is currently under
review in biological cybernetics about
that with car with sorry gregar Ser Pera
first auor with a bright mathematician
and we can do a demonstration and
actually derived theorems about that and
also simulations that show interesting
behaviors that depend on projective
parameters that will show that the
behavior of the agent uh depending on
the parameter will be more focused so
they will tend to always approach one
object because they're driven by this
anticipation of increasing information
through projective transformation uh but
uh uh uh with other parameters or values
of the parameters on the contrary they
start now oscillating between objects
they start losing focus as if they were
kind of ADHD uh so there is a deep link
between let's say um the evaluation of
space the appraisal of space uh um the
drives that are uh uh that unfold from
this information and the behaviors that
uh you have for instance approaching uh
uh uh and that geometry that very
geometry we are talking about yield that
type of thing so here we are talking
about what is typically described as
epistemic emotion basically curiosity so
we have Natural Curiosity and part of it
that drives behaviors is a result of the
very geometry that represent information
and appra it according to that theory we
I cannot enter into the detail on that
but you can also look on papers that we
wrote In what was that
2022 in uh uh the Journal of theoretical
biology in which we use little robots uh
to demonstrate
adaptive and maladaptive behaviors uh
with principles also derived from the
geometry and the free energy principle
or something equivalent uh uh to get a
wealth of affective behavior of approach
avoidance but also uh uh social
cognition you know you kind of we can
kind of simulate social anxiety um we
can we obtain joint attention Behavior
as a result of mutual perspective taking
uh and there are lot of things we could
account uh that we can use in this model
in in this framework to account for
emotion there is a lot of work ahead but
we believe that there is and we have
good reason to believe there is a deep
link between space and emotion that's
actually called Aesthetics that
Consciousness is a form of Aesthetics
where space and emotion are uh untangled
and that we can fairly well uh account
for many phenomena that relate to
emotion and behavior
through this model but that's sorry for
the long
talk that's great should I give my my so
answer is very much along the same lines
that emotion and space are deeply linked
um in the wave model I mean the project
the the model of space contains all of
space the external space and the
internal space of the body and an
important part of emotions is feelings
in the body and they are part of your
conscious awareness part of the uh the
wave model objective model just like the
others and so basically this the PW
Theory and I think the PCM says all
Consciousness is spatial we have qualia
but they exist in space you hear you
hear words you experience colors you
experience all of those and you
experience feelings all of them in space
so if you look at all the components of
emotion human emotion for instance the
words we
say to ourselves and the feelings we
have in our bodies they are all
represented in that comp that conscious
space so human emotion is a complex
story which perhaps we don't want to go
into but basically it comes down to the
way we experience it is in that model of
space and if I may I would have that if
you take the stpoint of pure
phenomenology and you ask yourself when
I experience an emotion for instance
anxiety or fear something very intense
that is very sent uh you can ask
yourself how much of that phenomenology
of that experience is actually quote
unquote reducible to some spatial
experience things for instance you know
the experience of the body with the
heart that starts P pounding in your
chest and you feel it stronger your
lungs that change there there you know
you breathe faster for instance and you
can feel that movement in your body and
all of that is special what you feel in
your your gut or your intestine get kind
of stretch or whatever you we have
metaphors but actually a lot of the
details of the phenomenology of emotion
of feelings let's say uh I believe is
actually spatial but it's overlooked
people don't think about it but in
particular think about bodily awareness
there is a lot of special stuff going on
here yeah I agree um and um mindful
meditation talk a lot about space and
talk a lot about the body I think they
put emotion in the right
place Carl or Ken want to add anything
or I can look for another question in
the live
[Music]
chat well I I have uh one question um so
I mean your current hypothesis is that
this wave is realized in the thalamus is
that is that right that's right yeah um
okay so that sort of um would you know
there's this kind of debate about
whether or not Consciousness is cortical
or or subcortical so this would
definitely be on the the sub I mean I
think there's a lot of sense in the
global workspace Theory and they were
talking originally about a workspace
involving the thalamus and the cortex
mhm I think it's it the Consciousness
really comes from the thalamus
integrating all that spatial information
yeah so it is down so what the the
follow-up uh but yeah that's fine with
me uh frankly but the follow-up question
is um well it's not exactly a followup
to that it's more a general question
about your way of thinking about it
how I mean I know maybe you can't really
answer this until we have a more
specific hypothesis about exactly what
kind of wave it is but could you say
something generally about how the
wave um integrates with or or what's
what's the right way to put it use
recruits and you know the kind of
computational apparatus of the brain so
that you know you end up you decide
to uh oh I'm going to reach out you know
yay far and grab this this bottle how
does the um how does you know
computationally speaking how does the
wave integrate yeah I think that's a
very good question and could have a very
long answer but basically um The Wave
integrates information from all the
sense sta so from your hands from your
ears from your eyes all that information
goes through the cortex and cortex
decides where it's coming from and
broadcasts signals back to the thalamus
and the thalamus wave integrates all
those signals together produce the
basian best model of what's happening at
this moment based on touch Pro
perception hearing Sound hearing vision
and so on so the computation it's an
integration of many sources of
information uh possibly in a cycle
between the thalamus and the
cortex okay but if if you need
to um you know for example program and
action so you you that's kind of the you
got your your
sensory um the integration of all your
sensory information now you need to
program an action how
do and maybe this is just my ignorance
how how do waves how can waves be used
in a way to well generate programing an
action and then give it back to your
your neurons I mean I've only got
beginnings of answers to that but
basically wave is very good for
representing 3D geometry and for
calculating displacements I know where
my hand is I know my coffee cup is so
the wave helps me calculate the
displacement which way I have to move my
hand to pick up the coffee cup so it's
that kind of spatial calculation that
the wave is always helping us do just to
move our
[Music]
limbs um I have a followup question on
that if I may can do you mind uh yeah no
go ahead go ahead you invoked earlier F
transform and inverse F transforms so at
least 3D for transform and inverse for
transform uh in order to do the encoding
and decoding uh to you know go move from
the wave to the neural substrates back
and forth um of course as you know uh
there is a limits in resolution uh when
you do a forier transform uh you have
the uncertainty principle uh that rules
the absolutely faal resolution that you
we can have of course it depends on the
number of sample I mean there are a lot
of arithmetics behind it you know you
can be more more and more precise as you
have more and more bits of uncoding if
you wish um so uh you you say that you
know neural classical neural theories
lack build
upon substrate that lack enough
Precision uh in spatial resolution for
instance to account for our experience
would you think that in the context of a
wave theory the type of uncertainty
principle that are attached to it could
cause a problem of resolution too or
that it's the the granular there is a
problem yeah there is a problem of
resolution I alluded to it in the slides
that is that if you got a minimum
wavelength Lambda and a diameter of the
sphere D the maximum Precision is Lambda
over D and that can't be infinite
Precision so that's the uncertainty
principle but the idea of the FIA
transform is not that something the
brain does a Foria transform it is the
fundamental bridging law for
Consciousness does the Foria transform
it says that Consciousness is a Foria
transform of the way full stop and for
transform is there in fundamental laws
of nature like like Quantum Mechanics
for instance so it's saying this is a
fundamental law of nature just like
quantum mechanics says momentum is a for
a transform position
so the the bridging law for
Consciousness says the form of
Consciousness is a for transform of the
way I I'll make an a short comment or
Carl do you want
to after you okay yeah just if so thank
you for the presentation and it's it's
really interesting on on many levels
first year you and the the paper goes
into more detail on this you lay out
what your priors are and kind of the
dependency structure to actually reach
at least an estimate of probabilities
which is it's it's really interesting it
gives a lot of opportunities for people
to dig in and say yeah I think that's
10% likelier no it's a zero this is not
possible and kind of close off a branch
of inquiry um and also this discussion
here about uh the algorithmic and the
substrate realiz ation interaction with
the substrate um and even this poly
computation idea of of the observer's
model of what's happening in a process
and kind of like the dark matter there
like The Observer might suggest that
there's a cryptographic process though
they couldn't decode it and then that
would have an entropy distribution that
that wouldn't be distinguishable in the
absence of the decryption from a noise
but it would be like still a hypothesis
kept alive and you could say I think
it's a 1% chance of this being the case
um one one thought is how high Precision
really is the spatial generative model
in that there could be visual
upscaling we know there's attention play
to make the periphery look sharp and
have color vision yeah and so it's
possible that especially for like
distant objects small objects that that
they could be
bundled and just seen as a assembly a
larger object if they're touching like
the car body and the wheel and then and
then the same way that in the periphery
color and visual attention seem to give
this extreme like wow that's like
exactly this angle if you were to go
over there with a protractor but that
could be as we're sort of seeing with
diffusion and generative AI models that
could be quite a low resolution
structural inference followed by a just
compatible visual realization that that
ALS and then just last
comment really interesting to explore
how does evolution and intergenerational
change shape the substrate that the
sense data wash over so that
non-stationary stable States whether
they're rate encoding of neuron or G
Electro and all these other even
potentially more exotic options however
those
stabilized wow you
you I mean th those are real questions
to investigate particularly the
Precision of our conscious experience
and how much is quotes an illusion but I
personally think that if you look at
something which is a straight line you
experience it as a straight line with
some kind of precision that's of the
order of
1% a deviation of 1% from a straight
line would show and so that's
a lower bound on the Precision of your
model but again there can be lots of
discussion about
this yeah
interesting Carl
any
thoughts well just a few sort of
um practical and specific questions um
so the nature of this wave if I wanted
to um model it I mean are we talking
about a standing wave are we talking
about a soliton are we talking about
spherical harmonics on a on the surface
of the um the thalamus are we talking
about you what kind of basis set might I
might might I use for for this kind of
wave even before asking questions about
what what the wave amplitude actually
means what so what what's the functional
mathematical form of this
way a very good questions whether it's a
standing wave or a moving wave I don't
know the nice thing about a Bose
Einstein condensate is that it acts like
a longlived quantum mechanical wave
function in other words it has phase
which can be detected and it preserves
phase for long times and the wave might
have to preserve phase in order to
represent positions if you have a
standing wave like cos Theta in some
direction in this sphere then there's an
ambiguity it represents plus Direction
and the minus Direction and what happens
to the minus Direction so I would rather
have phase in the wave like a Bose
Einstein condensate but they are very
deep questions and I don't need the
answers I mean we could start modeling
and and see what happens just propose
some answers uh basically you just need
a spherical volume that holds a wave
exitation with a certain maximum wave
vector
and we could try out standing waves
moving waves and so
[Music]
on I me what would
um differentiate um a condensate from a
formulation in terms of a Time dependent
scrolling a wave
equation um well I think your time
dependence Shing a w as as everybody
knows the problem with Quantum in the
brain is that decoherent smashes it in
10us 20 seconds but that doesn't happen
to a bone condensate a bone condensate
is a long lived Quantum
State and so that's you know an ordinary
Shing equation decoherence is going to
smash you in no time at all unless you
have some incredibly clever insulation
like in a quantum
computer right but I mean you know
lifting from the microscopic to the
macroscopic I mean that that would
suggest that you you need very very low
temperatures thermodynamically speaking
I mean you nobody just observed a BC at
room temperature yet but we've got close
and the idea is that nature might be
clever than we
are one angle perhaps from the quantum
Fe from from Carl and Chris fields and
others is and so what I heard in the qu
in the basis set question Carl was um
this brain region that hosts the
functionality or or a core aspect of the
functionality like one option is it is
like the the the wave is represented
inside of that sphere like just a
there's probably multiple way even that
could happen but it's like a little
reconstruction wave but symbolized
another option would be like a
holograph the representation of space is
encoded on the interface of that region
with other
regions and so that kind of surface is
maintained and stabilized and has has
information flowing through it and then
there wouldn't necessarily be some in
the middle but it'd be more like a
ripple on a Surface which was the the
Bas ass set
question Daniel that is very interesting
because in the thalamus there is the
thalamic reticular nucleus TRN which is
a thin skin around the surface of thalam
and you could just say that is holding
the surface
wave and the wave is projected inside
from the
surface it would be useful um if
um to engage Chris Fields here there are
two very distinct uses of the word
holographic here you could be referring
to the holographic principle yeah um
whereby all the information on the bulk
on the inside say of the
thalamus um was um on the surface on the
you know the reticular nucleus of the
thalamus for example or just on the
surface um you know in in one sense and
um and that is what the rest of the
brain sees and possibly Consciousness
sees um as AO but that's a very
different use of the the notion uh of um
a holographic projection using um um
constructive and D active interference
to to to encode things um so then you're
absolutely right my my my question was
really searching your um to distinguish
are we talking about um a wave function
um in the phala so are we talking about
um application of the holographic
principle to um the classical
information on the
surface of some bulk that was the
thalamus and you could then argue if you
if you wanted to that the bulk which can
never be observed from the outside
unless you are the phalus you never know
what's happening on the inside um you
could only observe what's what's on the
surface um um you know that would be a
different applica a different notion of
of the of of a wave theory that would um
certainly be consistent with Quantum
information Theory and also um
consistent with um um Chris Field's
inner screen hypothesis that could be
spatialized and endowed with with um a
in virtue of the fact that the um on the
holographic screen itself on the on the
surface there can only be classical
information and that information can now
be um cast in terms of classical basing
inference um but it also
um relates to repeat to Chris Field's
inner screen hypothesis um which is um
you know if you like taking Quantum
information theoretic principles uh and
trying to apply them to uh to
Consciousness that eludes the problem of
um
the of applying quantum mechanics that
is only relevant at the very small scale
or or for very precise or low
temperature systems uh you could if you
want to apply that kind of maths to um
macroscopic phenomena then you have to
apply it in a scale invariant context
and I think Quantum information Theory
would C would certainly do that so D yes
I was exactly sort of trying a probe are
we is the is PW red um the the um Bose
Einstein cond condensate variant of or
alternative vers version of uh the
projective
wave is that committed to Quantum
Mechanics or is it really um an um an
expression of um condensate like
Dynamics in the context of quantum
information Theory uh and if it is does
it live on a holographic screen or does
it live in the bulk and if it lives in
the bulk what what are these wave
functions over so these are the S
practical questions I was I was trying
to
get very interesting questions and it's
all to play for really I I have an open
mind about them but um my feeling is
that the becc is a way of getting past
this decoherence argument from tmar and
others that you know neurons have to be
classical because
of and the BC it it does work very well
as a memory that's that's the Practical
point of it and working memory I think
is what you need for
space awesome um perhaps each can give a
last round or thought like where where
do they feel this takes them or what are
they looking forward
to and uh Ken then David and then Carl
and then
Robert I yeah I don't have anything new
to add just that I find this really
interesting and I remember um reading uh
Karen Smith's book kind of arguing that
Bose Bose Einstein condensates might be
might be um important for understanding
Consciousness and thinking that among
the quantum mechanical hypotheses I like
that one the
best
so
praise but well as I said earlier I just
sort of have this kind of bias but I'm
totally willing to be talked out of it
um and uh yeah the the reason I mean I
don't want to go into the details but it
kind I think Karen Smith's concern was
about the unity of Consciousness
primarily and um also kind of made the
case that yeah as you were suggesting
that maybe um maybe as you put it nature
is clever than we are and there's some
way to realize that Bose Ein sign
condens it in the brain without it you
know without the decoherence uh issue
but anyway uh I'm just to say this is
all very um very fascinating to me and
and I am am happy to continue the
discussion next week right isn't it next
week
yeah thank you
Ken and for my part yes also looking
forward to continuations of the
discussion you know my um my direction
of questioning will be um something on
the lines I think both kenth and David
alluded to which is the um the link
between spatial
waves in the brain and the projective
geometry that they speak to and the
information geometry that underwrites um
belief updating and the basing mechanics
that that um inherit from from the free
energy principle U be it classical
mechanic
classical information processing or um
the you know looking at um using Quantum
information Theory to you know to read
um read belief updating I'm not sure I'm
going to get any answers but that's what
I'd be interested in hearing more about
and the process series we haven't talked
about Mortal computation yet so we need
to talk about Mortal computation oh
yes David any last
thoughts well there sort of a
of of a man who is 50 now and feels that
the more he learns the less he knows so
was predicted in all the books I had
read in my years uh and so I'm whole
open to that complex Universe I
certainly believe that nature is clever
than I am for sure and I find that
fascinating I I like the rational it's
not like you know there is a lot of
stuff about quantum mechanics and the
brain and Consciousness that to me has
always sended Wishy wasy if not
completely Waco uh uh but uh I came back
a bit from that I had a lot of like can
uh priors negative priors about it uh I
remember once in Tucson Arizona at at
the famous conference toward about the
science of Consciousness there were this
bunch of guys who called themselves they
were German the quantum Consciousness
Academy and they were all dressed in
black and they all you know headset and
microphone like that and they were like
speaking nonsense sense as like a cult
but I found that very fascinated because
I I I used to like very fascinating
sorry I used to like this conference
back in the day when it was very
psychedelic uh but that was kind of you
know and I come back to that because my
ignorance I'm becoming aware more and
more of my own ignorance uh I said well
why not and definitely I think that
maybe Carl can try to to to do that if
we could get chrisfield in the next call
he would certainly be among us the most
competent uh I tried to get gregar Ser
per uh to the call but he was not viable
uh he's a very bright mathematician and
he Master quantum mechanics like like if
it was you know I don't know it's
nothing for him or Daniel Bena would be
the best also with gregar but I'm afraid
I won't be able to have them here but I
think it would be very useful to have
some people like that who definitely
know more than me about those things and
Chris might be interested to join I
don't know car but looking forward to
the the next uh uh to the next
discussion one correction they were
Swiss David they were they weren't David
they weren't they
weren't what they were Swiss they were
Swiss Men In Black I think yes they kind
of look like people from The Matrix like
oh they were Swiss they were not German
they were Swiss yeah and they had they
had a leader they were always in contact
with Super H
wow okay word yeah please Robert and and
and we'll contact Chris but go for the
all your contribution that that's been
really fascinating I think the virtue of
this theory is that it is falsifiable in
other words if there's no wave in the
brain forget it this theory is wrong and
that's exactly the question we're going
to be looking at next week I look
forward to having your contributions
awesome thank you all see you at 16 UTC
on July
29th okay thank you thank you
bye for